Finding Aid for David R. Byrd Papers, 1930s-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
David R. Byrd Papers 1930s-2004, 1965-1973, 1981-1983
Byrd, David R.
9 oversize folders
1 portfolio
3.5 linear feet (in 4 boxes)
0565 Aa 2
David R. Byrd (1921-1987) was an African-American architect of churches, residential homes, offices, and schools in Washington, D.C. and Ann Arbor, Michigan. He served on the Board of Commissioners of Washtenaw County (1968-1972), and was an advocate for civil rights and affordable housing for the poor. This collection includes architectural drawings, reports, photographs, and personal and professional correspondence.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received from David R. Byrd's widow, Letitia Byrd (donor no. 9509 ), on September 16, 2004, with an additional donation on January 4, 2005.
The collection is open to research.
David R. Byrd (1921-1987) was born in Washington, D.C. After graduating from Hampton Institute in 1942, he remained in the Washington area, where he became a practicing architect in 1951, and a teacher at Springarn High School in 1952.
Byrd's early projects included residential homes, a medical office building, and the headquarters of the Capitol Cab Association. In 1959, Andrew Bryant, a graduate of Howard University, became a partner in Byrd's firm, and by 1964, the two men had $11 million in commissions for projects in the region (Box 1, folder "David R. Byrd and Andrew Bryant: Million Dollar Architects," magazine article).
In the 1960s, Byrd designed office buildings and schools. including an addition to the Rudolph Elementary School in 1965. However, the majority of his clients were churches, and Byrd earned special merit for his designs of the New Berean Baptist Church in 1968, and the Miles Memorial CME Church in 1970.
In 1966, Byrd married Letitia Johnson and moved to Ann Arbor. He was part of the "founding faculty" of Washtenaw Community College, and he served on the Washtenaw County Board of Commissioners (1968-1972) and the Ann Arbor City Planning Commission (1968-1971).
Byrd continued to design buildings after his relocation to Ann Arbor, including the New Hope Baptist Church, and an old farmhouse, which he restored, renamed "Sunny Pastures," and used as his office for the rest of his career. Byrd also built a small chapel near the farmhouse. At his death, it was renamed the "David R. Byrd Chapel," and bequeathed by his widow, Letitia Byrd, to the Episcopal Church of the Incarnation.
In 1981, David and Letitia Byrd were part of a group of Ann Arbor residents who founded the Ann Arbor Alliance for Achievement in Academics and the Arts, which provided scholarships for African-American students. Byrd also served on Ann Arbor's Human Rights Commission in early 1970s, and continued to speak out on behalf of civil rights and the need for affordable housing in Ann Arbor and other communities. He died in 1987 "following a lengthy illness" (Box 1, folder "Memorials of David Byrd," obituary, Ann Arbor News, May 17, 1987).
The David R. Byrd papers include correspondence, reports, drawings, plans, and photographs regarding the life of David Byrd, his career in architecture, and his civic activism. The papers contain material on churches and other projects Byrd designed in Ann Arbor and Washington D.C., documentation of his interest in city planning and zoning issues in Ann Arbor and Washtenaw County and his interest in the school system and the African-American community in Ann Arbor.
Subjects:
Byrd, David R.; African American architects.; African Americans--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ann Arbor Alliance for Achievement in Academics and the Arts.; Architects--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Architects--Washington (D.C.); Church architecture--Washington (D.C.); Washtenaw County (Mich.). Board of Commissioners.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
African Americans--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Byrd, Letitia.; Byrd, David R.; Churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Churches--Washington (D.C.); Detroit Observatory.
Genre Terms:
Architectural drawings.; Photographs.
- Biographical 1942-1988, 2000
  The Biographical series, 1942-1988, and 2000, (0.25 linear feet) is arranged alphabetically by topic. The series includes a two-volume "dossier" which Byrd assembled for the University of Michigan's Department of Architecture. The dossier includes documents and photographs from Byrd's life and professional career until the year 1972.
  - Dossier, volume one 1942-1972 (Box 1)
    (expanding folder includes photographs, correspondence, reports, and clippings)
  - Dossier, volume two 1958-1972 (Box 1)
  - Byrd, David R. 1921-1986 (Box 1)
  - Dissertation Proposal, Wayne State: "Employment Opportunities Available to High School Leavers, Age Eighteen Through Twenty-Two, in Architectural Drafting Occupations" 1978 (Box 1)
  - Memorials of David R. Byrd 1987-1988, 2000 (Box 1)
    (obituaries and other retrospectives on his life)
  - Michigan Registration for Architects 1969-1971 (Box 1)
  - Certificates and diplomas 1942, 1951-1952, 1963, 1970, 1987 (Box 1)
    (in oversize box 4)
- Board of Commissioners, Washtenaw County 1969-1971
  The Board of Commissioners, Washtenaw County series, 1969-1971, (0.25 linear feet) is a sequence arranged alphabetically by topic. The series contains records about specific problems of zoning and other civic matters which were addressed by the board or by its Property Committee.
  - District Court, Washtenaw County 1970-1973 (Box 1)
  - Elections 1970 (Box 1)
  - Maiden Lake, José Miranda 1971 (Box 1)
    (zoning dispute on residential property)
  - Police Training Academy undated (Box 1)
  - Property Committee 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - React Program 1970 (Box 1)
    (proposal to participate in citizens' band radio emergency channel initiative)
  - St. Joseph's Hospital 1970 (Box 1)
  - Superior Ambulance Lawsuit 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Superior Township Proposal 1969 (Box 1)
  - Washtenaw County Clothing Center ("House by the Side of the Road") 1970 (Box 1)
- Other Activities 1968-1983
  The Other Activities series, 1968-1983, (0.75 linear feet) is arranged alphabetically by topic and contains records about Byrd's public service. These records include ten folders about the Ann Arbor Alliance for Achievement in Academics and the Arts. There also documents concerning other organizations and groups, such as the Ann Arbor School District Safety Committee and the Black Contractors and Tradesmen Association. An expanding folder contains proposals for the development of the city of Ann Arbor (from a perspective circa 1965) and potential obstacles that might stand in the way of those proposals. The series also includes a copy of Byrd's 1968 grant application to the Department of Housing and Urban Development for a "model neighborhood" which would have provided resources to the poor during a time of strong city growth.
  - American Institute of Architects 1970-1973 (Box 1)
  - American Institute of Architects, Community Development 1972 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Alliance for Achievement in Academics and the Arts
    - General 1981-1983 (Box 1)
    - Agendas 1981-1983 (Box 1)
    - Board of Directors 1981 (Box 1)
    - Constitution and By-Laws undated (Box 1)
    - Corporation 1981-1983 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, Out 1979-1983 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence Received 1981-1983 (Box 1)
    - Logo undated (Box 1)
    - Membership 1981-1982 (Box 1)
    - Minutes 1981-1983 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Development 1965-1969, 1 expanding folder (Box 1)
    (proposals and potential obstacles to those proposals)
  - Ann Arbor Housing Rehabilitation Program 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Human Rights Commission 1975 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor, North Central Plans and Problems 1968 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor, North Side Planning Problems 1970 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor, Public Defender Program 1970 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor District Safety Committee 1970-1972, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Waiver Review Board 1979 (Box 1)
  - Black Contractors and Tradesmen Association, Washtenaw County 1970-1972 (Box 2)
  - Black Economic Development League 1970-1972 (Box 2)
  - City Planning Committee 1968-1971 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1970 (Box 2)
  - Manifesto undated (Box 2)
    (unattributed document, "To the White Christian Churches and the Jewish Synagogues in the United States of American and All Other Racist Institutions")
  - Model Neighborhood Grant Application to Department of Housing and Urban Development 1968 (Box 2)
  - Our Lady of Guadeloupe Community Center, Port Huron (MI?) 1971 (Box 2)
  - Republican Party, Washtenaw County 1970 (Box 2)
    (card indicating Byrd's selection to Executive Committee)
  - Speeches and Sermons 1969 (Box 2)
  - Washtenaw County Civil Defense Communications Readiness Plan 1968 (Box 2)
  - Washtenaw Community College 1968-1975 (Box 2)
- Projects circa 1958-1970
  The Projects series, 1958-1979(?), (0.75 linear feet) contains correspondence, legal agreements, photographs, and reports arranged alphabetically by project. Most of the materials concern the design and construction of the New Berean Baptist Church and the Miles Memorial CME Church in Washington, D.C.
  - Bettis House, Washington, D.C. undated (Box 2)
  - Day Care Center, James and Ruby Forshee, Ann Arbor 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - First Methodist Church, Ann Arbor undated (Box 2)
  - J. Raleigh Nelson Residence Restoration, Ann Arbor 1977 (Box 2)
    (correspondence)
  - Mazique, Margurite and Edward undated (Box 2)
    (Correspondence, clipping photograph. Margurite Mazique was David R. Byrd's sister.)
  - Miles Memorial Christian Methodist Episcopal. Church, Washington, D.C.
    - General 1965-1968 (Box 2)
    - Certificates of Payment 1967-1968 (Box 2)
    - Contract Disputes 1967-1970 (Box 2)
    - Contract Fees 1967-1968 (Box 2)
    - Letters and Reports 1965-1969 (Box 2)
    - Specifications undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - National Beauty Culturists League Memorial Building, Washington, D.C. undated (Box 2)
  - New Berean Baptist Church, Washington, D.C.
    - Certificates of Payment 1967-1968 (Box 2)
    - Change of Orders 1967 (Box 2)
    - Contract Fees 1962 (Box 2)
    - Letters and Reports 1965-1968 (Box 2)
    - Letters Received 1967-1968 (Box 2)
    - Specifications 1966 (Box 2)
  - Other Projects, Washington, D.C. 1958-1963 (Box 2)
  - Quorum Building, Magnaz Corporation, Ann Arbor 1970-1974 (Box 2)
  - Senior Housing Cooperative Apartments, Ann Arbor 1971-1973 (Box 2)
  - Walker, James, M.D. 1966-1972 (Box 2)
    (personal and project-related correspondence, legal agreements, and clippings)
- Photographs, circa 1930s-circa 1980s
  The Photographs series, undated, ca. 1930s-1980s (one set from 1972), (0.6 linear feet and 1 portfolio) contains photographs of David Byrd, the Byrd family, and architectural projects under construction and after completion. The series also includes a Portfolio of photographs of the Detroit Observatory from 1973. Oversize photographs are stored in Oversize Box 4.
  - Byrd, David undated (Box 3)
    (portrait and posed photographs)
  - Byrd, David, "Swearing In, 1972" (Box 3)
    (This title was on the original folder. The photographs are time-stamped December, 1968.)
  - Byrd, Letitia and family (?) undated (Box 3)
  - Byrd Family undated (Box 3)
  - Byrd Family at church (?) undated (Box 3)
    (also see Oversize Box 4)
  - Friends and Business Associates undated (Box 3)
  - Negatives undated (Box 3)
  - Politics and Other Activities undated (Box 3)
  - Projects, Churches undated (Box 3)
    (includes New Berean Baptist Church and Miles Memorial CME Church)
  - Projects, Commercial and Organizational undated (Box 3)
  - Projects, Churches undated (Box 3)
  - Projects, Residential undated (Box 3)
    (including Byrd House, Washington, D.C.) (also see Oversize Box 4)
  - Byrd Family at Church (?) undated (Box 4)
  - Photographs of David R. Byrd, unidentified projects, and a presentation undated (Box 4)
    (mounted photographs used in a presentation about a possible Underground Railroad site)
  - Portfolio of Washington, D.C. projects, c. circa 1965 (Box 4)
  - Projects, Churches undated (Box 4)
  - Projects, Day Care Center (?) 1979 (Box 4)
    (36 photographs of an unidentified site and accompanying two-page note)
  - Projects, Residential undated (Box 4)
  - Detroit Observatory, University of Michigan December, 1973 (Volume 1)
    (photographs collected in 1 portfolio)
- Architectural Drawings, undated, 1967, 1970, 9 oversize folders
  The Architectural Drawings series, undated (some materials, 1967 and 1970), (9 oversize folders) contains photographs, drawings, a certificate from West Virginia, and plans for the New Berean Baptist Church, the Miles Memorial CME Church, the New Hope Baptist Church. and the Community Service Office of the Black Economic Development League.
  - New Berean Baptist Church, Washington, D.C. undated, 3 folders (Folder 1)
    (plans and a drawing)
  - New Berean Baptist Church, Washington, D.C. undated, 3 folders (Folder 2)
    (continued)
  - New Berean Baptist Church, Washington, D.C. undated, 3 folders (Folder 3)
  - Miles Memorial CME Church, Washington, D.C. 1967, 2 folders (Folder 4)
  - Miles Memorial CME Church, Washington, D.C. 1967, 2 folders (Folder 5)
  - Unity Church of God in Christ, Ypsilanti, Mich. undated (Folder 6)
    (drawing)
  - Memorial Garden, First United Methodist Church, Ann Arbor undated (Folder 7)
  - Photographs, undated, and Certification, West Virginia, 1970 (Folder 8)
  - New Hope Baptist Church and Black Economic Development League Community Service Office (Folder 9)
    (plans)